<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.1">
    <info>
        <title>XForms Multiclient Blackjack Documentation</title>
        <author>
            <personname>Daniel Meint</personname>
            <email>d.meint@tum.de</email>
        </author>
        <author>
            <personname>Felix Hennerkes</personname>
            <email>ga38hom@mytum.de</email>
        </author>
        <author>
            <personname>Janik Schnellbach</personname>
            <email>janik.schnellbach@tum.de</email>
        </author>
        <author>
            <personname>Maximilian Karpfinger</personname>
            <email>maximilian.karpfinger@tum.de</email>
        </author>
        <orgname>Technical University of Munich (TUM)</orgname>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <!-- Daniel -->

    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Description of the case study</title>
        <!-- Daniel -->
        <para>We implement the popular casino game Blackjack as a multi-client web application.
            Globally, there are a variety of rulesets with slight differences. We seek to present
            the most universally accepted variation, commonly found in Las Vegas casinos.</para>
        <para>Up to five <emphasis>players</emphasis> compete not against each other, but separately
            against the <emphasis>dealer</emphasis>. The objective of each player is to draw cards
            and maximize the sum of their respective values (<emphasis>hand value</emphasis>)
            without exceeding a sum of 21 (<emphasis>bust</emphasis>). Players win by achieving one
            of the following final game states: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A hand value of 21 with only two cards
                        (<emphasis>blackjack</emphasis>)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A value higher than dealer's without exceeding 21</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A value less than 21 while the dealer busts</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>The game is played with a single deck of french playing cards. Number cards are worth
            their value, e.g. the seven of hearts is worth seven points, face cards (Jack, Queen,
            and King) are worth ten points, and an Ace can be counted as either one or eleven,
            depending on what is more favorable in a specific situation. A hand containing an Ace
            counted as eleven is referred to as a <emphasis>soft</emphasis> hand, because the value
            of the Ace will change to a one to prevent the player from busting if he was to draw
            another card and otherwise exceed 21. A card's suit is irrelevant in Blackjack.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Preparation</title>
            <para>Before the actual playing begins, players place their bets. Our version uses
                US-dollars as currency and does not limit players in the amount they want to bet. It
                does, however, prohitibt them from playing without betting at all. We will refer to
                this stage of the game as the <emphasis>betting phase</emphasis> throughout the
                following sections.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Course of a round</title>
            <para> At the beginning of the <emphasis>playing phase</emphasis> each player is dealt
                two cards face up. The dealer receives one exposed card that everyone can see and
                one hidden card.</para>
            <para>The dealer subsequently asks each player, going clockwise around the table,
                whether they want to improve their respective hand by drawing additional cards. Each
                player has the following options:
                <table>
                    <caption></caption>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <td>Action</td>
                            <td>Description</td>
                            <td>Condition</td>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td>Stand</td>
                            <td>Ends the player's turn</td>
                            <td>Always possible and automatically performed when the player
                                busts</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>Hit</td>
                            <td>The player receives another card from the deck</td>
                            <td>Availble if the player's hand value is less than 21</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>Double</td>
                            <td>The player doubles his bet and receives exactly one more card before
                                finishing his turn</td>
                            <td>Available if the player only has his two initial two cards</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>Insurance</td>
                            <td>The player puts a side-bet worth half his initial bet on the outcome
                                that the dealer has a Blackjack</td>
                            <td>Available if the player's hand value is less than 21 and the first
                                card of the dealer is an Ace</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>

                </table> If a player busts, they lose the round and have to pay their bet to the
                dealer</para>
            <para>After all players have finished their turn, the dealer plays in a predetermined
                manner: He draws cards as long as his hand is worth less than 17 points and must
                stand on a soft 17 or better.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Architecture</title>
        <!-- Felix -->
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>The component model</title>
        <!-- Max -->
        <section>
            <title>Modeling the model</title>
            <para> In a MVC-architecture the model has the control of the application's logic.
                Furthermore it is resposibel to store data in a database. In order to maintain data,
                several objects with unique functionality are needed. All these collaborating
                objects provide different attributes and methods. In the following the data model
                will be described at first. Thereon the design decisions will be discussed. The
                second part consists of the implementation of the game, followed by a discussion on
                implementation details and what problems were faced. </para>
            <para> The database consists of a list of games. For that a class
                    <classname>game</classname> is needed which stores every information about the
                instance of a blackjack game. A game object has multiple attributes and functions. <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><code>id</code> to distinguish games</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><code>state</code> stores the state of the game</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist> Regarding <classname>game</classname> functions, their main purpose
                is constructing,initializing and resetting game objects. Because every game object
                also stores all the attending players and a dealer, the functions essentially
                execute operations on all players. In addition to the basic functions,
                    <classname>game</classname> provides the function <function>evaluate</function>.
                However the logic of evaluating a player is sourced to the
                    <classname>player</classname> class. Another object stored in a game object is
                the chat. </para>
            <para> The <classname>player</classname> has the following attributes. <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><code>name</code> stores name of the player</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><code>state</code> stores the state of the player</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><code>insurance</code> stores wether or not a player chose to take
                            insurance</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><code>balance</code> stores the total balance of a player</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><code>bet</code> stores the player's bet in a round</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><code>profit</code> stores the player's profit in a round</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist> Another object stored inside the player is the players hand, which
                holds the cards. As to the <classname>player</classname> functions, contiguous to
                the constructors and setters, there are alot of functions that contain the game's
                logic. Depending on the game's state, a player can take several actions, which are
                passed over to the <classname>player</classname> class by the API. Following
                functions are supplied. <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><function>hit</function> draws another card for the player</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><function>stand</function> the player doesn't want more cards</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><function>double</function> doubles the player's bet and draws one
                            last card</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><function>insurance</function> the player takes insurance</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><function>evaluate</function> determines the player's profit</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist> Alongside the listed functions there are some helpers, which provide
                logic for finding the next player and joining or leaving a game. </para>
            <para> Since the players all play against the dealer, another class
                    <classname>dealer</classname> is required. It has no attributes, but it stores
                the deck of the game and likewise the players a hand object. Concerning the
                functions of the class, <function>evaluateInsurance</function> is a helper for
                evaluating a players profit. The function <function>deal</function> gives every
                player two cards and also draws for the dealer. </para>
            <para> The <classname>hand</classname> class has the attribute <code>value</code> which
                stores the value of the contained cards. On one hand this class provides helper
                functions for evaluating a player's hand. On the other hand it supplies the
                    <function>getOptimalSum</function> function that calculates the optimal sum of a
                hand. This is needed because the card Ace can have the value 1 and 11. </para>
            <para> The <classname>card</classname> class consists of two attributes. <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><code>value</code> stores the value of a card</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><code>suit</code> stores the suit of a card</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Design decisions and discussion</title>
            <para> why we chose to have object hand </para>
            <para> why we have usr and player </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Implementation</title>
            <para>deck is real not generating random cards</para>
            <para>optimal sum recursive</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Implementation decisions and discussion</title>
            <para>dealer drawing at first</para>
            <para>profit for front end</para>
            <para>how to deal with broke players</para>
            <para> problem of trying to replace node multiple time -> work around </para>
            <para> double and bust call next() -> problem of evaluate data not in db if it was last
                player </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>The component View</title>
        <section>
            <title>Modeling the component View</title>
            <!-- Janik -->
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Implementing the component View</title>
            <!-- Janik -->
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>The component Controller</title>
        <section>
            <title>Modeling the component Controller</title>
            <!-- Felix -->
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Implementing the component Controller</title>
            <!-- Felix -->
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Conclusions</title>
        
    </section>
    <bibliography>
        <!-- Beispiel -->
        <biblioentry xreflabel="BaseX" xml:id="BaseXHome">
            <bibliomisc>BaseX homepage. http://basex.org. Last accessed on 2019 June 16
            </bibliomisc>
        </biblioentry>
    </bibliography>
</article>
